Fei Liu

3180 Voigt Dr, La Jolla, CA 92122

▼ f4liu@eng.ucsd.edu 🞧 Github 🞓 Google Scholar

Research Focus

Robotics in system modeling, control, dynamics, physical-based simulation, autonomy, haptic teleoperation and mechatronics, in particular for surgical and biomedical applications.

Bio

Fei is a postdoctoral researcher at the Contextual Robotics Institute at University of California San Diego (UCSD). He is currently working on robotic autonomy for surgical applications, with semantic modeling, real-to-sim simulation, and advanced control techniques. Before that, he served as a research associate/postdoctoral scholar both at the Biorobotics Institute at Scuola Superiore Sant'Anna (SSSA), and the Center for Micro-BioRobotics at Italian Institute of Technology (IIT) in Italy. He finished his Ph.D. at Laboratory Ampère at INSA de Lyon, a French grande école and engineering university. He also worked as a senior control engineer and project director in a start-up company for the development of a robot for Endoscopic Submucosal Dissection (ESD) surgery, right after his PhD dissertation. He has published a number of journal/conference papers.

Education

Institut National des Sciences Appliquées de Lyon (INSA de Lyon)

Sep. 2013 - Sep. 2016

Lyon, France

• Thesis title: Dual-user Haptic Training System

• Supervisors : Prof. Arnaud Lelevé, Prof. Tanneguy Redarce, Dr. Damien Eberard

Institut National des Sciences Appliquées de Lyon (INSA de Lyon)

Sep. 2012 - Aug. 2013

Lyon, France

Master of Science in Robotics

• Thesis title: Teleoperation System Using Port-Hamiltonian Approach

• Supervisor : Prof. Arnaud Lelevé

Northwestern Polytechnical University (NWPU, 985 & 211 Rank)

Sep. 2008 - Jul. 2012

Xi'an, China

Bachelor of Science in Automation

Speciality: Automation and Inertial Navigation

Biorobotics Institute, Scuola Superiore Sant'Anna

Working Appointments

Postdoctoral Scholar

Dec. 2019 - present

Advanced Robotics and Controls Lab, University of California San Diego San Diego, CA, USA

Advisor: Prof. Michael Yip

Research Associate Scholar

Apr. 2019 - Nov. 2019

Pisa, Italy

Advisor: Prof. Filippo Cavallo

Postdoctoral Scholar

Mar. 2018 - Mar. 2019

Center for Micro-BioRobotics, IIT@SSSA, Italian Institute of Technology

Pisa, Italy

Senior Control Engineer & Project Director

Sep. 2017 - Feb. 2018

ROBO Medical Technology Co., Ltd

Shenzhen. China

Main works: Contol system design for single-port/cable-driven surgical robot and autonomous mobile robot with SLAM

Publications

Dissertation and Thesis:

- [PhD] Fei Liu, Dual-user Haptic Training System, <u>archives-ouvertes.fr/tel-01514992</u>, Ph.D. Dissertation, INSA de Lyon, 2017.
- [Master] Fei Liu, Cooperative Haptic Hands-on Minimally Invasive Surgery (MIS) Trainer, M.Sc. Thesis, INSA de Lyon, 2013.

To-submit/Pre-prints:

- [TS-J1] **Fei Liu**, Florian Richter, Fei Yin, Chong He, Cédrec Girerd, Michael C. Yip. Continuum Robot Shape Reconstruction and Tracking from Monocular Endoscopic Image Sequences. *IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters (RAL)*, To submit.
- [TS-J2] Xiao Liang, Shan Lin, **Fei Liu**, Dimitri Schreiber, Michael C. Yip. ODERegNet: an ODE-based Recursive Image Registration Network for 4D Lung CT. *IEEE Transactions on Biomedical Engineering (T-BME)*, To submit.
- [TS-J3] Zhaowei Yu, Dimitri A. Schreiber, **Fei Liu**, Alexander M. Grant, Michael C. Yip. An Underwater Remote Teleoperation Robot Arm with Rolling Diaphragm Actuation and End Effector Force Reconstruction. *IEEE/ASME Transactions on Mechatronics (T-MECH)*, To submit.

Journal Articles (\star shares the first author.):

- [J1] **Fei Liu***, Mingen Li*, Jingpei Lu, Entong Su, Michael C. Yip. Parameter Identification and Motion Control for Articulated Rigid Body Robots Using Differential Position-based Dynamics. *IEEE Transactions on Robotics* (T-RO). In revision. arXiv: 2201.05753.
- [J2] Fei Liu*, Entong Su*, Jingpei Lu, Mingen Li, Michael C. Yip. Differentiable Robotic Manipulation of Deformable Rope-like Objects Using Compliant Position-based Dynamics. to submit. *IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters (RAL)*. Submitted. arXiv: 2202.09714
- [J3] Florian Richter, Shihao Shen, **Fei Liu**, Jingbin Huang, Emily K. Funk, Ryan K. Orosco, Michael C. Yip. Autonomous Robotic Suction to Clear the Surgical Field for Hemostasis Using Image-Based Blood Flow Detection. *IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters (RAL)*, 2021. DOI: 10.1109/LRA.2021.3056057
- [J4] Sarmad Mehrdad*, Fei Liu*, Minh Tu Pham, Arnaud Lelevé, S. Farokh Atashzar. Review of Advanced Medical Telerobots. Applied Sciences, 2020. DOI: 10.3390/app11010209
- [J5] Angel R. Licona, Fei Liu, David Pinzon, Ali Torabi, Pierre Boulanger, Arnaud Lelevé, Richard Moreau, Minh Tu Pham, Mahdi Tavakoli, Troy McDaniel. Applications of Haptics in Medicine. Haptic Interfaces for Accessibility, Health, and Enhanced Quality of Life, Nov. 2019. DOI: 10.1007/978-3-030-34230-2_7
- [J6] **Fei Liu**, Angel Ricardo Licona, Arnaud Lelevé, Damien Eberard, Minh Tu Pham, Tanneguy Redarce. An Energy-Based Approach for n-dof Passive Dual-user Haptic Training Systems. *Robotica*, 2019. DOI: 10.1017/S0263574719001309

Conference Proceedings (\star shares the first author.):

- [C1] Jingpei Lu*, Fei Liu*, Michael C. Yip. Image-based Pose Estimation and Shape Reconstruction for Robot Manipulators and Soft, Continuum Robots via Differentiable Rendering. *IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA) 2023. Submitted.* todo
- [C2] Neelay Joglekar, Fei Liu, Michael C. Yip. Suture Thread Spline Reconstruction from Endoscopic Images for Robotic Surgery with Reliability-driven Keypoint Detection. *IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA) 2023. Submitted.* arXiv: 2209.13657

- [C3] Fei Liu*, Zihan Li*, Yuhai Han, Jingpei Lu, Florian Richter, Michael C. Yip. Real-to-Sim Registration of Deformable Soft-Tissue with Position-Based Dynamics for Surgical Robot Autonomy. *IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA) 2021.* DOI: 10.1109/ICRA48506.2021.9561177
- [C4] Jingbin Huang*, Fei Liu*, Florian Richter, Michael C. Yip. Model-Predictive Control of Blood Suction for Surgical Hemostasis using Differentiable Fluid Simulations. IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA), 2021. DOI: 10.1109/ICRA48506.2021.9561624
- [C5] Yunhai Han, Fei Liu, Michael C. Yip. A 2D Surgical Simulation Framework for Tool-Tissue Interaction. IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS) Workshop on Cognitive Robotic Surgery, 2020. arXiv: 2010.13936
- [C6] Jacob J. Johnson, Linjun Li, **Fei Liu**, Ahmed H. Qureshi, Michael C. Yip. Dynamically constrained motion planning networks for non-holonomic robots. IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS), 2020. DOI: 10.1109/IROS45743.2020.9341283
- [C7] Angel Ricardo Licona Rodriguez, Fei Liu, Arnaud Lelevé, Damien Eberard, Minh Tu Pham. Collaborative Hands-on Training on Haptic Simulators. 7th International Conference on Mechatronics and Control Engineering, Nov. 2018. DOI: 10.1145/3332305.3332318
- [C8] Fei Liu, Arnaud Lelevé, Damien Eberard, Tanneguy Redarce. An Energy Based Approach for Passive Dual-user Haptic Training Systems. IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS), Oct. 2016. DOI: 10.1109/IROS.2016.7759771
- [C9] Fei Liu, Arnaud Lelevé, Damien Eberard, Tanneguy Redarce. A Dual-user Teleoperation System with Online Authority Adjustment for Haptic Training. 37th Annual International Conference of the IEEE Engineering in Medicine and Biology Society (EMBC), Aug. 2015. DOI: 10.1109/EMBC.2015.7318574
- [C10] Fei Liu, Arnaud Lelevé, Damien Eberard, Tanneguy Redarce. A Dual-user Teleoperation System with Adaptive Authority Adjustement for Haptic Training. 4th International Workshop on Medical and Service Robots, Jul. 2015. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-30674-2_13
- [C11] Fei Liu, Yinan Sang, Jie He, Jie Fan, Ruichao Li, Xiongyi Cui, Haoyu Li, Jie Chen. Northwestern Polytechnical University Team Entry for the 2012 AUVSI International Aerial Robotics Competition, International Aerial Robotics Competition (IARC) Symposium, Aug. 2012. Link
- [C12] Fei Liu, Haoyu Li, Li Li. Modeling of the Snowboard Course, International Mathematical Contest in Modeling (MCM) Symposium, Apri. 2011

Research Experience

PostDoc, ARCLab &

Advanced Robotics and Controls Lab, UCSD

 ${\bf Dec.\ 2019-present}$

San Diego, CA, USA

- Modeling of deformable, rigid, articulated, fluid object using position-based dynamics (PBD), in particular for surgical scenes, i.e., soft tissue, membrane, blood and tools etc.
- Differentiability for the PBD simulation using adjoint method based on chain-rule.
- Simulation framework using NVIDIA-Flex, PBD, and self-written constrained based solver.
- Real-to-sim transfer techniques using non-rigid perception, registration, and tracking.
- Closed-loop controller design and validation using field robots, such as da Vinci Reseach Kit (DVRK), 7-dof Baxter Robotic Arm.
- Continuum robot project: Shape reconstruction using projection of geometrical primitives (cylinders, circles etc.) and perform visual servoing control.

Biorobotics Institute, Scuola Superiore Sant'Anna

Apr. 2019 - Nov. 2019

Researcher, Assistive Robotics Lab &

Pisa, Italy

- Simultaneous localization and mapping (SLAM) of mobile robotic platform under ROS.
- Autonomous initialization through computer vision approaches using aruco markers (QR codes).

- Autonomous navigation of the mobile robot including path planning, obstacle avoidance.
- Shared control theory development and implementation of the mobile platform.
- Design of PHP/HTML-based web user interface.
- Experimental tests in Verona, Italy.

Center for Micro-BioRobotics IIT@SSSA

PostDoc, Istituto Italiano di Tecnologia &

Mar. 2018 - Apr. 2019

Pisa, Italy

- Modeling and control KUKA LWR4+ robotic arm using ROS and Gazebo: motion control, trajectory planning, master-slave
- Modeling and control of flexible continuum surgical tool: static tension-deflection model, Euler-Lagrange dynamics, port-Hamiltonian based control.
- Analysis of several continuum structure prototypes: variation of design (notches, single-backbone, articulated).
- Develop teleoperation framework using haptic devices (Sigma.7).
- Preliminary study of simulation platform for flexible surgical tools using SOFA (Simulation Open Framework Architecture \mathfrak{G}).

Control Engineer & Project Director

Aug. 2017 - Feb. 2018

• ROBO Medical Technology Co., Ltd

Shenzhen, China

- Develop teleoperation of a single-port abdominal robotics surgical system using haptic devices (i.e., PHANTOM Omni, Novint Falcon, Omega.3) and joysticks (i.e., Logitech G Extreme 3D, Microsoft Xbox).
- Modeling and control of a tendon-driven articulated end-effector: kinematics, motion control, master-slave.
- Model-based uncertainties identification and compensation: hysteresis, friction.
- Modeling and control of a 4 dofs positioning arm (parallel mechanisms): kinematics, motion control, master-slave.
- Caculation of the RCM point of positioning arm.
- Modeling and control (based on gait analysis) of a powered lower limb orthosis for rehabilitation.
- SLAM algorithm (build on ROS) of autonomous mobile robots for medical transportation in hospitals.

PHD Thesis: Dual-user Haptic Training System

Sep. 2012 - Sep. 2016

Advisors: Prof. Tanneguy Redarce, Prof. Arnaud Lelevé, Dr. Damien Eberard

INSA de Lyon, France

- Focused on modeling and control aspects with/without time delays.
- Developed real-time experiments both with Matlab/Simulink, ROS and Chai3D.
- Published three international conference papers, and one journal paper.

Group Leader: DJI RoboMasters Mobile Manipulation Challenge

Aug. 2014

Design of Autonomous Mobile Robot Using SLAM and Computer Vision Approach.

Shenzhen, China

• Dajiang Innovations Technology Co., Ltd (DJI)

- Developed SLAM framework for mobile robots (chariots) u on ROS.
- Implemented fast on-board object tracking and recognition algorithms.
- Developed multi-robot coordination and searching algorithms.

Master Thesis: Cooperative Haptic Hands-on MIS Trainer

Sep. 2012 - Aug. 2013

Master Internship at Ampère Laboratory

INSA de Lyon, France

- Designed teleoperation system using port-Hamiltonian approach.
- Implemented control algorithms with haptic devices (PHANTOM Omni).
- Developed real-time experiments using Matlab/Simulink.

Team Leader: International Aerial Robotics Competition (IARC)

Aug. 2012

A Low Cost Autonomous Quadrotor UAV-Icarus

Peking, China

- Mathmatical modeling of a self-made low cost laser rangefinder based on geometric caculation for environment mapping.
- · Autonomous control of the quadrotor using environment mapping and detection algo- rithm (wall and window detection using point cloud analysis).

• Awarded Innovative Design.

Undergraduate Internship

Sep. 2011 - Jun. 2012

Image Meta-data Feature Extraction for Content-Context Based Image Retrieval

NPU, Xi'an, China

• Implemented image processing and classification algorithms.

Team Leader: International Mathematical Contest in Modeling (MCM)

Feb. 2012

Optimal Design of U-shaped Snowboard Course

NPU, Xi'an, China

• Awarded Meritorious Winner (First Prize Mention).

Team Leader: Robocup 3D Simulation Group

Sep. 2010 - Jun. 2012

Robocup Soccer Center of NPU, Simulation Robots of Robocup Soccer

NPU, Xi'an, China

- Designed gait algorithm of NAO (Humanoid) robot.
- Developed control strategies for simulated soccer competition under linux platform.
- Awarded **Third Prize** in China Open 2011.

Project Leader: Student Project of Chinese Ministry of Education

Nov. 2011 - Jun. 2012

Mining Methods for Gene Expression Profile Classification

NPU, Xi'an, China

• Implemented statistical and computing algorithms related to data mining.

Project Leader: Student Project of Chinese Ministry of Education

 $Nov.\ 2010-Jun.\ 2011$

Path Planning of Mobile Robot

NPU, Xi'an, China

• Implemented path planning algorithms of mobile robot (A^* , genetic algorithm, fuzzy control etc.

"Freescale Cup" National Smart Car Design Competition

 $\mathbf{Dec.\ 2010-May.\ 2011}$

Design and Control of an Intelligent Car for Path Following

NPU, Xi'an, China

• Awarded **Third Prize** in NPU Open 2011.

Research Assistant: Laboratory Project

Sep. 2010 – Jun. 2011

 $Navigation\ of\ Unmanned\ Aerial\ Vehicle\ (UAV)\ Based\ on\ Digital\ Map$

NPU, Xi'an, China

• Supervisor: Prof. Suilao Li, College of Automation, NPU

Research Assistant: Laboratory Project

Sep. 2009 – Jun. 2010

Design of Intelligent Vehicle and Autonomous Navigation

NPU, Xi'an, China

• Supervisor: Prof. Suilao Li, College of Automation, NPU

Professional Activities

Journal/Conference Reviewer

2016-present

- IEEE Transactions on Robotics (T-RO)
- IEEE Transactions on Mechatronics (T-MECH)
- IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters (RAL)
- IEEE Transactions on Medical Robotics and Bionics
- Control Engineering Practice
- \bullet Robotica
- International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)
- ullet American Control Conference (ACC)
- International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR)
- IFAC Workshop on Lagrangian and Hamiltonian Methods for Nonlinear Control (LHMNC)

Poster Presentation 2015 – 2021

- Emerging Frontiers in Research and Innovation (EFRI) All-Teams Workshop, Virtual, USA.
- 37th Annual International Conference of the IEEE Engineering in Medicine and Biology Society (EMBS), Milano, Italy.

Oral Presentation 2015-2021

- 2021 International Conference on Robotics and Automation, Virtual, Xi'an, China.
- 7th Summer School on Surgical Robotics (SSSR 2015), Montpellier, France.
- 37th EMBS Ignite Sessions, Milano, Italy.
- 4th International Workshop on Medical and Service Robots (MESROB), Nantes, France.

Volunteer May. 2014

• 20th World Olympic Collectors Fair, Lausanne, Switzerland.

- IEEE Membership 2017 present
- IEEE Student Membership. 2015 2016
- EMBS Membership. 2015 2016

Supervision Activities

PhD Students

Yu Huan: currently senior engineer at United-Imaging Healthcare Co., Ltd., Shanghai

Mar. 2018 - Mar. 2019, Scuola Superiore Sant'Anna

• Topic : Design and control of flexible minature surgical tools (continuum robot).

Master Students

I Junning Wu: currently second-year master student at UCSD

Sep. 2021 – present, Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering (ECE), UCSD

• Topic: Bi-manual close-loop control of dual-arm suturing using physical-based simulation.

Xiao Liang: currently second-year master student at UCSD

Sep. 2021 - present, Department of ECE, UCSD

• Topic: Reconstruction of 4D lung motionu using neural-ODE integration.

Chong He: currently second-year master student at UCSD

Sep. 2021 – Aug. 2022, Department of Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering (MAE), UCSD

• Topic: Shape reconstruction of catheter robot using monocular images.

Mingen Li: currently first-year PhD student at University of Minnesota, Twin Cities

Jan. 2021 – Jan. 2022, Department of ECE, UCSD

• Topic: Simulation and control of articulated rigid body robots using position-based dynamics.

? Yunhai Han: currently first-year PhD student at Georgia Institute of Technology

Jan. 2021 – Jan. 2022, Department of MAE, UCSD

• Topic : Simulation framework using position-based dynamics using self-written constraints based solver.

Entong Su: currently second-year master student at UCSD

Jan. 2021 - Jan. 2022, Department of ECE, UCSD

• Topic: Simulation of rope-like object using position-based dynamics for shape control.

in Zihan Li: currently software algorithm engineer at OmniVision Technologies, Inc.

Jan. 2020 – Nov. 2020, Department of ECE, UCSD

• Topic: Registration method for real-to-sim transfer applications of deformable tissue manipulation.

in Jingbin Huang

Mar. 2020 - Nov. 2020, Department of ECE, UCSD

• Topic: Modeling and control of surgical tool for suction based simulation of blood fluid.

in Sean Liu: currently lead engineer at Hyperspec.ai

Jun. 2020 - Sep. 2020, Department of ECE, UCSD

• Topic: Reconstruction of a catheter robot shape using projection of geometrical primitives.

Undergraduate Student

in Neelay Joglekar: currently third-year undergraduate student at UCSD

Jan. 2021 – present, Department of ECE, UCSD

• Topic: Dynamic model of rope-like objects using cosserat rod theory and surgical thread reconstruction.

In Yutong Zhang: currently first-year master student at UCSD

Jan. 2021 – present, Department of Computer Science, UCSD

• Topic : Simulation platform using libIGL/openGL rendering and visualization for various objects, i.e., rigid, articulated robots, deformable, fluid etc.

Bryan Yuan: currently software engineer at Qualcomm Inc.

Jan. 2021 - May 2022, Department of ECE, UCSD

• Topic : Coding of the gradients computed for position-based dynamics constraints.

In Nemanja Babic: currently senior engineer at Hypertherm Associates Inc.

May. 2015 – Aug. 2015, Research Internship, University of Ottawa & INSA de Lyon

• Topic : Simulation of haptic systems using CHAI3D.

Research Techniques and Relevant Skills

Computer Languages: Python, C++, C, MATLAB/Simulink, PHP

Sofware Skill: PyTorch, Linux, LaTEX, ROS, Gazebo, MoveIt, Chai3D, SOFA, OpenCV, Open3D, OSQP etc..

Hardware Experiences: da Vinci Reseach Kit (DVRK), 7-DOF Baxter Robotic Arm, KUKA LWR 4+, NDI Electromagnetic Sensor, Phantom Omni, Omega.3 & Sigma.7 (Force Dimension), Novint Falcon, MAXON Motors, EPOS Drivers, Aurora, SICK Laser Range-finder, IMU sensors, etc..

Languages

Chinese: Native English: Advanced French: Intermediate B1 Italian: Beginner

Media Publicity